Good morning everybody or whatever it's called.
All right, today's דף daf is כ"ט, kaf tet, 29, we start
about
one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven lines before the lines get wide
on כ"ח עמוד ב', kaf chet amud bet, perfectly at the new
topic.
So we've discussed you need to שחט shecht two סימנים simanim in
mammals, one סימן siman in birds, there was even a question about
whether biblically birds need שחיטה shechita at all, and you don't have
to do any שחיטה shechita by fish, and we discussed the position
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about cutting the major blood vessels that
the גמרא gemara said is not a requirement of שחיטה shechita per
se but as a way of draining the blood. Now we get
to the last part of the משנה mishna which says that you
don't have to sever the entire סימן, siman, it's enough to sever
the majority of it or the majority of the two of them
if it's a mammal. And now we look at a larger conceptual
question about the concept of majority. So let's take a look. חצי
אחד בעוף, chatzi echad be-of, so by the two dots, כ"ח עמוד
ב', kaf chet amud bet, thank you so much. Okay, the majority
of one in birds and the majority of two in mammals. אתמר,
itmar, it was taught. רב Rav said מחצה על מחצה כרוב. mechtza
al mechtza ke-rov. How about if it's exactly half? Now interestingly, the
משנה mishna seemed to address the case of exactly half. The משנה
mishna said majority yes, half no. We'll bracket that for a minute.
But now we're going to ask the question: by majority do you
mean majority or by majority is half enough? All right, so exactly
half. So רב Rav says
it is just, it's
like the majority, רובו ככולו, rubo ke-kulo, and half is like the
majority, so half is good enough to be the majority and a
majority is like the whole thing. So it's sort of like by
that chain you get to that exactly a half counts. Okay, so
רב Rav says half is good enough. רב כהנא Rav Kahana said
מחצה על מחצה אינו כרוב, mechtza al mechtza eino ke-rov, half is
not like the majority. Now we're going to explain what this debate
is about. רב Rav said מחצה על מחצה כרוב, mechtza al mechtza
ke-rov, half is like the majority. הכי אמר ליה רחמנא למשה. hachi
amar lei rachmana le-moshe. This is what God said to משה, Moshe,
meaning this is how we understand the requirement of שחיטה shechta and
שחיטה shechting a majority: לא תשייר רובו. lo tishayer rubo.
Do not leave the majority remaining. Make sure that you don't have
a majority left when you do each סימן. siman. But רב כהנא
Rav Kahana said מחצה על מחצה אינו כרוב, mechtza al mechtza eino
ke-rov, half is not like the majority. הכי אמר ליה רחמנא למשה.
hachi amar lei rachmana le-moshe. No, this is what God said to
משה. Moshe. It's so funny the way they sort of like it
sounds like this is the requirement. It's like we were up there
at הר סיני Har Sinai and we have different versions of what
God said. This is what God said to משה: Moshe: שחוט רובה.
shchot rubah. Slaughter the majority, cut the majority. Now
this could, this question, as is all questions, is majority enough? Or
the question that we've raised before which we're going to actually get
back to in a day or two which is: when we say
majority counts, does it count because it's as
like you did everything, or because fundamentally you only need the majority?
All of those types of questions, the answer could be different in
every different area of הלכה, halacha, right? You could have majority could
be good enough for שחיטה, shechita, it could be good enough for
this, could be good enough for that. There could be a different
explanation of it in all the cases. Here too, especially why the
גמרא gemara is zooming in on this is what God said to
משה, Moshe, שחוט shchot the majority, don't leave the majority, it sounds
like it's a specific question about the requirements by שחיטה. shechita. We
will see in a second that the גמרא gemara is going to
broaden it to another case and abstracts it as a general question.
Now if I were to ask why, so if it's not just
a limited question like what is the criteria by שחיטה, shechita, which
then is relatively arbitrary, could be this, could be that, whatever the
criteria is, that's what it is. But if I wanted to make
it a slightly more general question, should half work or not work?
Okay, and in a place where I think you know conceptually what
that's about. It seems like the גמרא gemara here is trying to
describe the difference. And the difference is the following. It's sort of
like the case I've talked about before of the excluded middle which
is: what are we positively defining? Are we positively defining the criteria
required to make it good, or are we positively defining the conditions
under which it's no good, the פסולים, psulim, the invalidities, the problems?
So if I were to positively define the conditions to make it
good, right, I would say you need to slaughter the majority then
it's considered like you've totally cut it. If I'm describing the conditions
to make it bad, then I might say if the majority is
left over, you haven't done it. So it doesn't have to be
that way obviously but that first of all is exactly what the
גמרא gemara is saying and there's a certain logic to that. The
one that you are positively defining usually leads to having higher criteria.
Let me give you another example, okay? Let's say just to take
a total random example,
an אתרוג. etrog. And there's a problem with an אתרוג, etrog, you
know that if it has let's
say a broken פיטם, pitam, it's no good. Okay, so how do
I describe that? Do I say the פיטם pitam has to be
complete? Or do I say if you have a broken פיטם, pitam,
it's פסול? pasul? Sounds like the same thing. But let's say you've
got an ambiguous case. It's half-broken, okay? So if I'm saying the
פיטם pitam has to be complete, well half-broken isn't complete. No good.
So which one you're describing often, you know, often means that that,
you know, it creates the higher criteria and anything less than that
is either okay or not okay depending on which way you're going.
That seems to be what the גמרא Gemara says. If you are,
well no, that's the debate then. Which one are we defining? No,
listen, no, what? Listen. So רבא Rava says... so
רב Rav says מחצה על מחצה כרוב. mechtza al mechtza kerov. מחצה
על מחצה mechtza al mechtza is רוב. rov. Why? Because God said
to משה, Moshe, "Don't leave a majority over." Meaning what has been
positively defined is the פסול, psul, the invalidity. So
don't leave too much over. How much is too much? A majority.
If you leave too much over, you haven't done it. So anything
less than the majority, exactly half, is okay. Whereas the other approach
says,
"No, half is no good." Because God said to משה, Moshe, as
it were, like what means what we're positively defining is what makes
it valid. So in order to be valid, you have to שחט
shecht the majority. So anything less than the majority is not good.
So this actually does seem, like I said, the answer could be
different in different areas of הלכה, halacha, but the way to, I
think, conceptualize this is: are we positively defining the criteria for making
it good, which creates high criteria and anything that's in somewhat of
a grey area is not good? Or are we positively defining the
criteria to make it bad, which means that anything in a grey
area will be good? And that's exactly how this debate is being
framed here. Yes?
Another issue, for something that's a continuous measure like the amount of
a pipe that you've שחט, shechted, right, you're never going to be
exactly half. There are cases though where you will, such as if
you're, where you're going to be round numbers such as when you're
making tithes from a finite and number of apples. Right.
So that's an interesting question, which is our the indeterminacy of is
it, do we know if a case that looks like half is
it really half or not? Is that your point? Okay, that's excellent.
The גמרא Gemara is going to get to that in a minute.
But right now we're not even up to that yet. Yes.
We said before that all animals start from a חזקה chazaka that
it's not...
no, no, no. That's different. That's
true. It starts from a חזקת טרפה chazakas treifa and you have
to prove that it's שחט. shechted. But when I have to prove
it's שחט, shechted, what checklist do I have to go through? Does
the checklist say "make sure you've שחט shechted the majority," or does
the checklist say "make sure you haven't left the majority over"? Okay,
so are we defining for it to be good? Are we defining
"you have to do this to make it good"? Or are we
saying "no, if you did this wrong, it's no good"? So the
גמרא Gemara is saying is the one that you are going to
focus on defining, right, means that anything less than that will be
in a different space. So if you're defining what makes it good,
if it's in a grey zone, it's no good. If you're defining
what makes it no good, then if you're in a grey zone,
it will be good.
Well, I mean, I would still think they're starting from the fact
that you need to make it good, right? Because it starts its
life as bad. I understand.
No, but then when you say, "Well, what makes it good?" "You
left over." No, those are different issues about what
you
have to prove and what you define as the criteria.
It's a very important nuance, this, you know, רובו ככולו rubo k’kulo
and מקצתו כרובו...
miktzaso k’rubo... Well, we're going to get to רובו ככולו rubo k’kulo
and מקצתו כרובו. miktzaso k’rubo. Well, all right, so let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
תנן, Tnan, first wide line after the parenthesis. תנן, Tnan, we taught
in our משנה. mishna. So our משנה mishna seems to answer the
question. Our משנה mishna says חצי אחד בעוף ואחד וחצי בבהמה, chatzi
echad b’of v’echad v’chatzi b’veheimah, if you do half by a bird
or one and a half by a בהמה, beheimah, a full one
plus a half, so even though the end you had 1.5, it
doesn't matter because you needed a majority of each one, it doesn't
matter the total
amount, you don't sum it up like that, פסולה, psulah, invalid. Now
that's very clear. It says if it's half, it's invalid. אי אמרת
מחצה על מחצה כרוב, I amart mechtza al mechtza kerov, if you
say half counts like the majority, אמאי פסול, amai pasul, why is
it invalid? הוי ליה רוב, havi leih rov, it's majority. Yeah, the
משנה mishna is very clear. Majority is no good. So the גמרא
Gemara says מדרבנן. miderabbanan. Nah, the משנה mishna could be rabbinically it's
no good. דאמרי לא אתי למיעבד פלגא, d’amri lo ati l’meivhad palga,
because if we allow, you know, if we allow exactly majority, you're
going to do a little less than exactly majority. So
we require... I mean exactly half, you're going to do a little
less than exactly half. So we require a majority to ensure that
you do at least a half. But that's rabbinic. Biblically, the claim
is half would still be fine. אמר רב קטינא, Amar Rav Katina,
so רב קטינא Rav Katina said תא שמע, ta shema, let me
prove it from another case. חילקו לשנים והן שוין, Chilko l’shnayim v’hen
shavin, and this is where it becomes a problem, not a problem
but whatever, strange, that the גמרא Gemara doesn't limit this question to
שחיטה. shechita. It assumes that it's going to be the same answer
in different fields of הלכה. halacha. Now of course, every field the
way we conceptualize majority and half could be different, but the גמרא
Gemara is now jumping. Now what's this case? This is a case
of a pottery vessel, he's talking about actually an oven, but a
pottery vessel that becomes טמא. tamei. You might remember that you cannot
put a pottery vessel in a מקוה mikvah to make it טהור.
tahor. The only way it becomes טהור tahor is if it's considered
broken. How is it considered broken? If there is not the majority
of it still around. Well, let's say there is exactly... it's split
exactly down the middle. 50%, two big pieces exactly 50%. Okay, is
it considered to be broken or not broken? So again, you could
conceptualize that. What does it mean to be broken? Does it mean
the majority of it has been... broken off, okay, and in this
case the majority hasn't been broken off because 50% is still there.
Or does it mean that the majority of it is present? And
in this case, the majority isn't present. So are you defining, you
know, as it were, the positive criteria or the negative criteria? So
let's take a look. So if they, if you divide it into
two, והם שוין veheim shavin and they're exactly equal halves, שניהם טמאין,
shneihem tme'in, they both retain their טומאה. tumah. לפי שאי אפשר לצמצם.
lefi she'i efshar letzamtzem. Now here comes חנן's Chanan's point, which is
it is impossible to determine. אי אפשר לצמצם i efshar letzamtzem gets
to our human inability to exactly measure. So whenever the גמרא Gemara
deals with this question of what if something is exactly half, it
has to deal with both what is the criteria in principle and
will we ever know that it's exactly half? We think we're measuring,
but we, but you know, we think we're determining it's half, but
how do we know? Like we're limited, we're human, and maybe it's
exactly 50.001%, how would we know? Now, אי אפשר לצמצם i efshar
letzamtzem is not only about being half; it's about anything that requires
real precision. Like for example, there's a question about בכור. bechor. What
happens if you have twins, by בהמה beheimah or whatever, by a
person, and they both come out at the exact same time? Which
one is the בכור? bechor? Now, the first question is: did they
really both come out at the same time or just we're not
able to determine? אפשר לצמצם efshar letzamtzem or אי אפשר לצמצם? i
efshar letzamtzem? Okay, do we assume that if for us it looks
like it was exact, that we do assume exact, or we assume
no, no, no, one was definitely bigger or smaller, one was first,
the other was second, we just don't know? We just don't know,
then you deal with it like a ספק. safek. You don't really
have the interesting, you know, legal question of exact same because we're
saying it wasn't the exact same, it's we're just ignorant of it.
So that's a general question of אפשר לצמצם efshar letzamtzem or not.
This big תוספות Tosafot here tries to figure out what's our general
stance by that idea. Do we generally assume אפשר לצמצם efshar letzamtzem
or not אפשר לצמצם? efshar letzamtzem? One, one point that תוספות Tosafot
makes which the גמרא Gemara makes just to introduce another factor because
we're not going to go into detail about it, is whether it's
בידי אדם bidei adam or בידי שמים, bidei shamayim, which means: are
we manipulating and controlling the situation? Then we might more say אפשר
לצמצם. efshar letzamtzem. If we're cutting and we want to know did
we cut half or not, right, or we're maybe breaking something in
half, maybe if we control it, we more can get a certain
precision out of it. But if it's like two twins being born
and we're not in control, right, and it's just like did they
come out at the same time or not at the same time?
So the ability to measure when we're not in control of the
situation, there we might say אי אפשר לצמצם. i efshar letzamtzem. Anyway,
that's one distinction תוספות Tosafot has, but that's a question how do
we rule.
Okay, so here, רב פפא, Rav Papa,
that's his basic inclination, although he has some contradictions in different sources.
So, yeah, it comes up a lot. So it says, חילקו לשנים,
chilko lishnayim, so let's see what this means, what this says. If
it was divided into two, this תנור, tanur, והם שוין, veheim shavin,
and they're exactly equal halves, שניהם טמאין, shneihem tme'in, you have to
assume both are טמא. tamei. לפי שאי אפשר לצמצם, lefi she'i efshar
letzamtzem, you don't really know. One is smaller, one is bigger, the
bigger one is טמא, tamei, the smaller one is not. But since
we don't know, therefore we have to assume they're both טמא. tamei.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says fine, that's because we don't
know. What would it be if we did know? האפשר לצמצם, ha'efshar
letzamtzem, presumably if we knew that they were both exactly half, the
הלכה halacha would be different. Well, what's the only possibility of the
difference of it being both being טמא? tamei? You can't say one
is טמא, tamei, one is טהור, tahor, if they're exactly half, they
have to be the same. So the implication is is that if
we did know they were exactly half, טהורין, tehorin, you'd have to
say both were טהור. tahor. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי טהורין,
amai tehorin, why are they both טהור? tahor? זיל הכא איכא רובא
וזיל הכא איכא רובא. zil hacha ika ruba vzil hacha ika ruba.
So if half counts like the majority, so then they should both
be טמא tamei according to that idea that half counts like the
majority. They shouldn't both be טהור. tahor. So אמר רב פפא, amar
Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa says no, no, no, תרי
רובי בחד מנא ליכא. trei rubei bechad mana leika. You can't say
that you have two halves, each one is the majority. Now what
does that mean? So תוספות Tosafot says this really shifts our understanding
and this is really a little bizarre. A was interesting, bizarre that
it went bizarre, but whatever. Interesting that the גמרא Gemara jumped from
the area of שחיטה shechitah because presumably how do we deal with
a case of exactly half to be different in different areas of
הלכה? halacha? But what's also bizarre is the way the גמרא Gemara
is shifting its conceptualizing of the issue. Until now we said, which
is beautifully I think articulated in the positions of רב Rav and
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, that the idea of saying half, it depends:
are we defining the invalidity or are we defining the validity? So,
for example, in this case of saying is a תנור טהור, tanur
tahor, you could say, right, you could say that as long as
it's not the majority still there, if the majority no longer remains,
it's טהור. tahor. Now if you conceptualized it that way, if it's
no longer the majority there it's טהור, tahor, you could have both
are טהור. tahor. Neither one has the majority, neither one is still
considered the תנור. tanur. To be considered the תנור tanur you need
the majority. Neither one is the majority, each one is... they're both
טהור. tahor. So what does this answer mean, oh you can't have
two things that are רוב? rov? תוספות Tosafot says from this the
גמרא Gemara is shifting gears. From here the גמרא Gemara is saying
it's not when we say majority is enough, it's that you know,
we're really just defining the problem and if it's the majority you're
okay. When we're saying majority is enough, what we're saying is: רוב
rov is like the whole thing, and majority is like רוב. rov.
You understand the difference? Meaning... Going back to my to my like
אתרוג esrog case, right, which I use the issue about like are
we defining if an if the פטום pitom is perfect, it's you
know is is intact. It's good, or are we defining no, if
the פטום pitom is broken. And that would be the difference what
if it's like quasi-broken. So here we're saying no, no, no, that's
not true. Everybody agrees we're saying the פטום pitom has to be
intact. But the one who says that quasi-broken is okay is because
he says quasi-broken is also quasi-intact and quasi-intact counts like intact. So
again we're not we're not defining that one is defining this criteria,
the other is defining that criteria. We're all saying in principle you
need to שחט shecht the majority of the trachea or the esophagus.
It's not like if you leave over the majority it's it's no
good. You need to שחט shecht the majority. The only argument is
50% is close enough that it counts as if it's the majority.
Now that's not as satisfying of an explanation, but that also explains
why the גמרא Gemara felt free to go from an area of
שחיטה shechita to an area of like טומאה tumah and pottery vessels.
Because then it's a much more universal position, right? 50% counts like
the majority. That's a more like universal position, not are we defining
this or defining that. And that's why the גמרא Gemara says you
can't have two 50%s because two 50%s are two majorities. So if
I'm going to say the oven is טהור tahor because since 50%
broke off it's like the majority broke off, so I can't say
by both of them it's like the majority broke off. That's logically
contradictory. So therefore I can't have them both טהור. tahor. So what
the גמרא Gemara did in this little line here is it universalized
the question, and by universalizing the question we're no longer asking which
part are we defining, the problem or you know the good part
or the bad part, we're making a generic statement 50% is considered
like majority. Once we're making that generic statement which we have from
other fields, and then we could also say but you can't say
it on both halves, because if you say it on both halves
you can't say both halves is considered like, you know, the majority
broke off, that would be logically contradictory. But it's also a problem
let me I should also say is you don't even need the
other half. If you're saying 50% is like the majority, then you
then it's a problem to say it even on one half, right?
Because which 50%?
Right. Right. So if you said the logic is 50% is majority,
so 50% is שחט shechted is good. 50% is not שחט shechted
is like the majority is not שחט. shechted. Half broke off it's
good. Half is still there it's not good. So it's a very
strange move that the גמרא Gemara does here. Okay, and I don't
have a good answer, I was much happier with the first way
I formulated it. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes on from
this.
תא שמע Tashma yes. The word majority, yes. How do you define
it?
Is it 50% or 50% plus epsilon? That's exactly the point. But
to say 50% is majority, that is what the גמרא Gemara is
suggesting now is the position of רב. Rav. Okay. So תא שמע,
tashma, come and hear. שחט shachach חצי chatzi גרגרת gogeret ושהה vesha
בה bah כדי kedei שחיטה shechita אחרת. acheret.
So you שחט shechted what? גרגרת, gogeret, what did I say? Anyway,
so you שחט shechted half of the trachea and you waited to
the time it takes to do a שחיטה shechita which is שהייה
shehiya which is a
פסול. pasul. וגמרה Vegamrah and you finished it. שחיטה shchitah so כשרה
kesherah it's valid. Now let's repeat again why it's valid. Normally שהייה
shehiya is a פסול. pasul. But
remember
by the trachea it could be cut half as long as it's
not the majority and not be a טרפה. treifa. So if you
were to have to say that the whole thing was one process
from the time you began to you end you had a שהייה
shehiya it's invalid. But because the trachea you can cut half and
it's still not a טרפה treifa you don't have to make it
one process. So you say when I cut half and I didn't
do a good שחיטה shechita yet, okay, so let's just view that
as an accidental cut. That's not a שחיטה. shechita. It was nothing.
It was an accidental cut. So now this animal has a cut
trachea but only half of it, so it's not a טרפה. treifa.
Now I come back a day later or an hour later or
whatever it is, ten minutes later and I שחט shecht it. Okay
that's a new act. It's a new act, I'm שוחט shechting an
animal with a cut but it's not a טרפה treifa and I
did a good שחיטה. shechita. So the reason שהייה shehiya is not
a problem is because you're allowed now because you don't have to
look at it as one process. You could look at it as
the first process wasn't שחיטה, shechita, it didn't make it a טרפה,
treifa, it was only half, and the next process that was the
act of the שחיטה. shechita. So that's what it says, you did
half and then you finished it, it's valid because the second thing
is really considered to be a new act and it's not a
problem of שהייה. shehiya. ואי אמרת Vi'amarta so let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does with this and if you say מחצה כמחצה כרוב
mechatzah ke-mechatzah ke-rov that half counts like the majority, אתפלי itpalei so
then you made it a טרפה treifa because you made half of
the
half of the esophagus is cut right now again and now why
a טרפה treifa why don't we say it's a valid שחיטה shechita
because the גמרא Gemara is assuming that we're talking about a בהמה
behemah like a cow. So if you cut half of the trachea
and then you stopped and resumed, so you've already made it a
טרפה treifa because the trachea is half cut. So the גמרא Gemara
says no מי סברת misavrat בבהמה b'behemah what makes you think we're
talking about a cow lo בעוף b'of we're talking about a bird
and then ממה נפשך miman nafshach either way you go. אם מחצה
כמחצה כרוב im mechatzah ke-mechatzah ke-rov if exactly half counts like a
majority הוי ליה רובא haviley ruba then you שחט shechted the majority
of a trachea. And it's shechted. אם חציים חתך אינו כרוב, im
chatzyam chatach eino k'rov, if half is not like the majority, which
is what I was saying before, לא עביד ולא כלום, lo avid
velo klum, so you didn't do a שחיטה, shechita, but not only
did you not do a שחיטה, shechita, you didn't make it a
טריפה, treifa, because the trachea is only a טריפה treifa when the
majority is cut. So you cut exactly half, it's not a שחיטה,
shechita, but it's also not a טריפה. treifa. And now you can
go and you can resume later and finish it off.
I'm sorry, wait, what's the difference between a בהמה behema and an
עוף? of?
Oh, by a בהמה, behema, you have to cut the trachea and
the esophagus. So by the בהמה, behema, if you cut, if you
said that the רוב rov was like a majority, you cut, I
mean, half was like the majority, when you cut the trachea, it's
considered like the majority is cut and therefore it's a טריפה. treifa.
The only way you save it from being a טריפה treifa is
to consider your שחיטה shechita as a continuous process. But as soon
as you consider your שחיטה shechita a continuous process, you're incorporating the
שהייה shehiya in the middle, the pause, and then you have a
פסול שחיטה. psul shechita. Right? By the עוף, of, the way you
save the situation is you say you paused, your next thing is
a new act. But
if you're a בהמה behema and you have to cut both, you
can't say the new thing is a new act because it would
be, right, a טריפה treifa if you cut the majority, and therefore
you have a problem of either טריפה treifa or שהייה. shehiya. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So we're still not,
we still haven't resolved it. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear.
הרי שהיה חצי קנה פגום, harei shehaya chatzi kaneh pagum, half of
the trachea
was like cut, exactly the case, except here you didn't do it,
it was cut through some other means. So it's half but it's
not yet a טריפה treifa because it's only half. והוסיף עליו כל
שהוא, ve'hosif alav kol shehu, and you added a tiny bit, got
from 50 percent to 51 percent, וגמרו, ugmoro, and you finished it.
שחיטתו כשרה, shechitato keshera, it's valid. So now we're back to our
question. ואי אמרת חציים חתך כרוב, ve'ee amart chatzyam chatach k'rov, if
half counts like a majority, so how was it not a טריפה
treifa if it started with a half-cut trachea? טריפה הויא, treifa havya,
it's a טריפה. treifa. So therefore now we're going into a third
field because טריפה treifa is not the same as שחיטה. shechita. Right?
We went to ovens, we talked about שחיטה, shechita, now we want
to know there's a פסול psul by the trachea, if it's half,
if it's majority cut, it's considered a טריפה. treifa. What if it's
exactly 50 percent cut? So we're assuming that that's the same question
that we can equally apply this question in all fields. So we're
saying, oh look, here's a trachea that's 50 percent cut. If 50
percent counts like majority, that should be considered majority cut and it
should be a טריפה, treifa, but it's not a טריפה. treifa. So
how do you explain that? So finally the גמרא Gemara distinguishes between
the area of הלכה. halacha. אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava
says, שאני לעניין טריפה דבעינן רוב הניכר לעיניים. shani l'inyan treifa d'beinan
rov hanikar l'einayim. No, טריפה treifa is different. טריפה treifa to be
a really make it טריפה, treif, when we say you need a
majority, it has to be a visible majority, which means not just
a formal majority. We could say
50 percent is like a virtual majority, but it has to be
a real majority in order to be a טריפה. treifa. Because that's
about the real question. If you want, you could sort of say
like this, there it's like it's sort of like when we dealt
once before about
going by majority in cases of health issues. You can't use legal
fictions when you're dealing about real questions about biology and health. There
it's a real question of what really is the story. So if
the reality is that an animal will die as a result of
a half-cut טריפה, treifa, so there it's not enough to say well
legally 50 percent counts like half. I mean, I'm sorry,
I just did, if it would die as a result of a
majority cut trachea, thank you. You can't say legally 50 percent counts
like majority. It's a real question of whether it will survive or
not. So if we say majority we mean real majority. Okay? So
there we say everybody would agree that majority really needs majority.
רוב הניכר לעיניים rov hanikar l'einayim means like really obvious? Or like
obvious, or if you're like really looking.
Meaning you could also say that 51 percent wouldn't be enough, you
would need 60 percent. So רוב הניכר לעיניים rov hanikar l'einayim could
mean different things. In this context it seems to just mean like
51 percent. A real majority, not something that counts as if it
were a majority. Yes, Charlie.
But this is a leniency.
Right, so it's not just saying right we're being strict for טריפות
treifas or whatever. We're just saying that טריפה treifa is something that
has to do with a real issue of can it live or
not. So it's not enough to say well 50 percent counts as
if. If it's a real question, it needs to be 51 percent.
And the real issue rests on majority, it has to be a
real majority, not a virtual majority. Yes.
So this is a perfect time. Is it correct that what we're
talking about in all this is not
how
we're allowed to slaughter animals, but how we're allowed to slaughter animals
for food consumption?
I assume the question would always be what would the first question
mean if it weren't food? I mean the גמרא Gemara said yesterday,
for example, if you wanted to use bird blood and you were
interested in the blood and not eating the meat, then the only
way to effectively do that is not do שחיטה. shechita. So is
the question that since we're always told that שחיטה shechita is about
צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim and here, that it's not true
because then it would be required if we also weren't doing it
in the context of trying to eat the meat?
Even more narrowly though the question of legal status versus reality of
the viability of the animal for the procedure is irrelevant because of
the legal status of what we're allowed to consume.
Right. I mean you are true that טריפה treifa is the end
even if it's describing the viability or not, in the end it
affects legal status. So why can't you say that you also go
by a formal rule by טריפה treifa as well? So the גמרא
Gemara is effectively going to ask that question in the next line,
okay? It's going to say if you need to if you're going
by vitality and real issues by טריפה, treifa, then you should go
by vitality types of questions by שחיטה shechita as well. You can't
distinguish between them based on that, which is the flip of your
point. But it's essentially the same, like yeah these are all either
legal questions or if you don't want to make them legal questions
then fine then you still can't answer why the cutting of the
סימן siman is different than the טריפה treifa question because then it's
a question about the real issue of vitality. Yes.
So how did the initial cut happen? What was the animal and
then a שוחט shochet said, 'Well it's good enough I can start'?
Yeah. How'd it get cut? I don't know that doesn't tend to
interest the גמרא. Gemara. It fell on a piece of glass or
something, I don't know how it happened.
But the argument
would be that if you don't have the majority of the trachea
or esophagus cut it can still survive. Okay, so let's see what
the גמרא, Gemara, so the גמרא Gemara tries to get out of
it by saying, 'Oh no, no, no, טריפה treifa you can't just
apply normal rules to.' So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye says back, ולאו כל שכן הוא? Velo
kol shekein hu? Is it not a כל שכן? kol shekein? ומה
טריפה דבמשהו מיטרפה היכא דבעינן רובא בעינן רוב הניכר לעיניים, Uma treifa
debimashehu miterfa heicha debeinan ruba beinan rov hanikar leeinaim, by טריפה treifa
that sometimes because it's about vitality that's exactly why sometimes even a
tiny hole is a problem depending on which organ it's in. Like
in the esophagus a tiny hole is a problem. So
there little problems should be bigger issues. So we should certainly and
even there you're going to say, 'Oh it's when you need a
majority you need a real majority. Fifty percent is not enough.' So
בשחיטה דעד דאיכא רובא לא מיכשרא, beshchita de'ad de'ika ruba lo michshara,
that it's the exact opposite by שחיטה. shechita. By שחיטה shechita we
say little cuts aren't are never an issue. You need to achieve
cutting the majority of it.
לא כל שכן דבעינן רוב הניכר לעיניים, Lo kol shekein debeinan rov
hanikar leeinaim, how much more so should you need a true majority?
So we've got a problem, which is it's interesting though notice that
the what causes the גמרא Gemara to reverse itself is not anything
by שחיטה shechita itself, although the simple sense of our משנה Mishna
said yes, fifty percent is not enough, you need majority. But in
the end what really pushed the גמרא Gemara there was in other
places where you needed a true majority and not fifty percent. So
by universalizing the question the גמרא Gemara has said, 'Oh there are
other cases where you need a true majority so by שחיטה shechita
as well you also need a true majority.' So therefore so what
is the debate then between רב Rav and who was it? רב
כהנא? Rav Kahana? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, Ela, you're right,
דכולי עלמא מחצה על מחצה אינו כרוב. dekuli alma mechtza al mechtza
eino kerov. You're right. By שחיטה shechita and by maybe a lot
of other cases fifty percent is not majority, majority means real majority.
וכי איתמר דרב ודרב כהנא, Vechi itmar deRav udeRav Kahana, so then
what did רב Rav and רב כהנא Rav Kahana debate? A very
narrow case. לענין פסח איתמר Le'inyan Pesach itmar regarding a קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. Okay, totally different case, right, which by the way this
is a fascinating issue for those people that do academic תלמוד, Talmud,
right, because רב Rav and רב כהנא's Rav Kahana their statement could
mean something totally different based on the context. רב Rav said מחצה
על מחצה כרוב, mechtza al mechtza kerov, רב כהנא Rav Kahana said
מחצה על מחצה אינו כרוב. mechtza al mechtza eino kerov. So if
you happen to put that statement on our משנה Mishna in חולין,
Chullin, they're debating how much שחיטה shechita do you need to do?
If you happen to put that statement on a משנה Mishna in
פסחים, Pesachim, they're going to be debating how many people have to
be טמא tamei in order to bring a פסח בטומאה, Pesach betuma,
right? So which context you put that statement totally changes their debate,
and that's an interesting issue for people that do academic תלמוד, Talmud,
which is like how the גמרא Gemara knows or assumes different ways
of putting contextualizing statements where the intrinsic evidence internal evidence does not
make it clear what the original context was. So the גמרא Gemara
basically so my point is you might think, 'Oh that's like crazy,
the גמרא's Gemara redefining it.' But it's not so crazy because their
original statement didn't define the context, so it's saying well maybe the
context was completely different than we assumed. So here was the original
debate of רב Rav and רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, the גמרא Gemara
saying by פסח. Pesach. Because it says לענין פסח איתמר le'inyan Pesach
itmar because here's what the משנה Mishna says הרי שהיו ישראל מחצה
טהורים ומחצה טמאים, Harei shehayu Yisrael mechtza tehorim umechtza temeim, not the
משנה Mishna excuse me, here's the way to make the statement. Behold
let's say the people were exactly half טהור tahor and half טמא.
tamei. Now the principle is if a majority of people are טמא
tamei then they go to פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. If the majority
of people are טמא tamei you bring the קרבן פסח בטומאה. Korban
Pesach betuma. If a minority are טמא tamei the people that are
טמא tamei go to פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Let's say it's exactly
fifty-fifty. By the way that you can count, right? You do an
exact count you get a whole number fifty-fifty טמא tamei and טהור.
tahor. So do you bring the פסח בטומאה Pesach betuma or do
you go ahead and have them go to the טמא tamei people
go to פסח שני? Pesach Sheni? So what's the הלכה? halacha? רב
אמר מחצה על מחצה כרוב Rav amar mechtza al mechtza kerov fifty-fifty
is like רוב rov and therefore the half that is טמא tamei
it's like the majority are טמא. tamei. Now here's where you have
contradictory רובס, rovs, right? The half that are טהור tahor they're all
טהור tahor the half that are טמא tamei it's like everybody's טמא.
tamei. So do you bring the פסח בטומאה Pesach betuma or not?
So what רב Rav actually says is those that are טהור tahor
have to bring it בטהרה betahara those that are טמא tamei bring
it בטומאה. betuma. Okay, so those that are טמא tamei it's like
they're the majority of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael it's like all of
ישראל Yisrael is טמא tamei they bring it בטומאה. betuma. But those
that are טהור tahor it's like all of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael
is טהור tahor so they have to bring it בטהרה. betahara. That's
what רב Rav says. And רב כהנא אמר מחצה על מחצה אינה
כרוב. Rav Kahana amar mechatzah al mechatzah einah kerov.
It's not like the majority, that those that are טמא tamei have
to bring it in the פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. והא מהי טעמא
דרב? Ve-ha mai ta'ama de-Rav?
What is רב's Rav reason there to say that the half that
are טמא tamei gets to bring it now and don't have to
wait till פסח שני? Pesach Sheni? דכתיב, De-chtiv, the verse says איש
איש כי יהיה טמא לנפש. ish ish ki yihyeh tamei la-nefesh. If
a person is טמא, tamei, he brings it in the פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. איש נדחה, Ish nidcheh,
only when you're considered to be a person in the minority, ואין
ציבור נדחין, ve-ein tzibur nidchin, not when you are a ציבור. tzibur.
So 50%, you're no longer a minority. Notice by the way, it's
the same way the גמרא Gemara started. If you define whatever you
define means that you're leaving the 50% on the other side of
the definition. So if I'm defining minority individuals go to פסח שני,
Pesach Sheni, as soon as you're 50% you're not individuals. Okay? If
I define the opposite, no, no, no, when the ציבור tzibur is
טמא, tamei, that's when you get to do it now. Well, it's
not the ציבור, tzibur, you're only 50%. So again it gets to
the question of what am I defining? Am I defining you have
to be the ציבור, tzibur, then you're not, you're only 50%? Or
am I defining no, no, no, only if you're an individual then
you go to the next פסח? Pesach? You're no longer an individual,
you're 50%. So it gets back to the earlier issue of what
am I defining and the 50%, the ambiguous cases, go on the
other side of the definition. But here it's specifically linked to a
פסוק pasuk because the פסוק pasuk says individuals, it allows 50% to
be on the other side. But in general the גמרא Gemara is
saying רב Rav would say 50% does not count and you need
a real majority. Now that's all very nice except תוספות Tosafot points
out there are other גמרות Gemarot where 50% does count. Like for
example, a classic case in עירובין Eruvin where it's an issue of
מחיצה. mechitzah. By מחיצה mechitzah it has to be a certain height
or whatever etc. Let's say you have around a courtyard to be
considered that it's fenced in to carry on שבת, Shabbat, not מחיצה
mechitzah for carrying on שבת Shabbat or those types of issues. What
if it says now the מחיצה mechitzah has to actually seal off
the space? What if the מחיצה mechitzah is made like by poles
that are spaced? Okay, and they're right, split, is that what it's
called? No. What? No, okay fine, it's got spaced poles. And the
way it is, now we're not going to do לבוד lavud like
it's within three טפחים, tefachim, assume not, that there are breaks in
the fence. Okay? So it has to, does it, so there's a
concept of majority, but what's the הלכה? halachah? If the majority is
exposed, it's not a מחיצה, mechitzah, or do we say that the
majority has to be closed for it to be considered a מחיצה?
mechitzah? And the difference again would be what if it's exactly 50-50?
And there the גמרא Gemara comes out that 50-50 is okay. So
תוספות Tosafot points out, you know, again the problem that you don't
always have the same answer. But what bothers תוספות, Tosafot, which would
have bothered us, is that the גמרא Gemara here universalized the question.
There's no problem saying that different areas of הלכה halachah have different
conclusions with how to deal with exactly 50%. The problem is that
the גמרא Gemara here universalized it and that led the גמרא Gemara
to reframe the whole issue and make it just about פסח Pesach
because you got a פסוק, pasuk, and in other places actually we
do rule differently about 50%. Yes, Charlie.
This is one place I would, this is an example where I
would expect to hear ספק דרבנן לקולא. safek de-rabbanan le-kula.
Well, the ספק safek issue is when you get to אי אפשר
לצמצם, i efshar letzamtzem, which is we know what the law is
but we can't determine. Since we can't determine, we're going to be
strict. Okay? But that's like a second level question. What happens if
we can't get the facts? The first level question is what's the
actual law if it was certainly exactly 50%? Okay? You're right, in
the end of the day it might not matter so much if
we always have to be strict or whatever, but, but you know
here we're talking about in the principle. So again the גמרא's Gemara
question here is how do you deal with, now what really the
earlier question should be is how do you conceptualize the idea of
majority, which we'll get to later. But once we've established that majority
is enough, how do you deal with 50%? And either that could
be framed as the question of what are we defining, are we
defining you know what makes it valid or what makes it invalid?
So the gray cases go on the other side of the definition.
That's the way the גמרא Gemara started out, or is it more
of a universal issue that is 50% in general considered close enough
to majority to be like the majority? And therefore it's a universal
question, except as the גמרא Gemara ended, well almost universal, not by
פסח Pesach because there it says individuals and תוספות Tosafot says and
not by a few other places in the גמרא Gemara where it
says the opposite.
What?
Yeah, all those cases, right. The answers are different. No they couldn't
be דבי הוריות, de-vei Horayot, ברוב ציבור? be-rov tzibur?
I don't know, you could have, I don't know why the גמרא
Gemara didn't do it. Okay. Now we go on. רוב אחד בעוף.
Rov echad ba-of. Okay, so the end of the משנה Mishnah says
like the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, if you did the majority
of one in a bird or a full one and half—I'm sorry,
right, it said
one and a half doesn't count, but if you did the majority
of one in a bird and the majority of two in a
בהמה beheimah it is good. So the גמרא Gemara says תנינא חדא
זימנא, tanina chada zimna, that was what we said in the beginning
of the משנה, Mishnah, רובו של אחד כמוהו. rubo shel echad kemohu.
The משנה Mishnah starts by saying the majority is good and ends
by saying the majority is good. So you know, why do you
have to repeat it? So אמר רב הושעיא אחד בחולין ואחד. Amar
Rav Hoshaya echad be-chullin ve-echad. Now
the one is talking about חולין chullin *Chullin*, that by non-sanctified animals
and that majority is enough, and one is talking about sacrifices. וצריכא
*Ve-Tzricha*, you need to say both. And here we get to the
issue that was being raised, that as opposed to חולין chullin, *Chullin*
where it's about trachea and esophagus, by קדשים kodashim *Kodshim* you really
care about the blood, right, because you gotta get the blood. וצריכא
*Ve-Tzricha*, you need both. דאי אשמעינן חולין chullin *De-Ee Ashmeinan Chullin*, if
it just said by non-sanctified animals, התם הוא דסגי ליה ברובו *hasam
hu de-sagi lei be-rubo*, there majority is enough, משום דלאו לדם הוא
צריך *mishum de-lav le-dam hu tzarich*,
because you don't care about whether you're going to get blood out
of the animal or not. אבל קדשים *Aval Kodshim*, by קדשים *Kodshim*
דדם צריך *de-dam tzarich*, that you need to get the blood out
to do the זריקה *zrika* of the blood, אימא לא תסגי ליה
ברובו *eima lo tisagi lei be-rubo*, maybe majority is not enough, maybe
you have to cut fully through, עד דאיכא כולו *ad de-ika kulo*,
you have to cut fully through, so it tells you that even
by קדשים *Kodshim* majority is enough. And now you could say the
reverse. ואי אשמעינן בקדשים *Ve-Ee Ashmeinan Be-Kodshim*, if it just said by
קדשים *Kodshim* majority is enough, משום דלדם הוא צריך *mishum de-le-dam hu
tzarich*, because you need the blood, that's why you need the majority.
אבל חולין דלדם לא צריך *Aval Chullin de-le-dam lo tzarich*, but by
חולין *Chullin* that you don't need blood, אימא בפלגא סגי ליה *eima
be-palga sagi lei*, maybe you don't need majority, maybe fifty percent suffices
like we've just debated but concluded that fifty percent is not enough.
קמשמע לן *Kamashmalan* that fifty percent, that majority is both needed by
חולין *Chullin* and sufficient by קדשים *Kodshim*, you only need majority. Now
what of course fascinating is if it were about the need for
blood that that should lead to a redefinition that you have to
cut the trachea and esophagus more is a little bizarre because in
order to get out the blood it's not about going deeper into
the trachea and esophagus, it's about going deeper
into the throat or the neck and cutting more blood vessels and
cutting the arteries or the veins. So it would be a little
funny that because I needed blood, if I thought the issue was
blood, it would have led me to רב יהודה'ס *Rav Yehuda's* position,
right, that you had to cut whatever it was, either the jugular
vein or the carotid artery. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying,
well maybe if you need blood the Torah would have demanded I
cut the trachea and esophagus deeper because that would have then led
to me cutting the neck deeper and would have led to more
blood. So it's a little funny that that would have been like,
that that would have led to a definition which was sort of
indirectly addressing what the concern was. But anyway the conclusion is that
that's not the case, that whether חולין *Chullin* or קדשים *Kodshim* majority
suffices.
Just the fact the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
didn't seem to differentiate between חולין *Chullin* and קדשים *Kodshim*.
Right, but the point is I might have thought to differentiate, so
therefore it like reiterated this is always all that you need. Okay,
now obviously it's reading in, it's not even talking about קדשים *Kodshim*,
but the reiteration is saying that that's all you need. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says האי בחולין והאי בקדשים *hai be-chullin ve-hai be-kodshim*.
So we're not, it's not enough to say it was reiterated, we're
saying one line is talking about חולין *Chullin*, one line is קדשים
*Kodshim*. Which is which? אמר רב כהנא *Amar Rav Kahana* מסתברא רישא
בחולין וסיפא בקדשים *mistabra reisha be-chullin ve-seifa be-kodshim*. The beginning part is
by חולין *Chullin* and the end is by קדשים *Kodshim*. ממאי *Mi-mai*,
how do you know, how do you know this?
מדקתני *Mi-de-ktani*, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says השוחט *Hashochet*, right? How does
the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* read? It starts with as you can see
the name of our פרק perek *perek*, השוחט אחד בעוף ושנים בבהמה
ורובו של אחד כמוהו *Hashochet echad be-of u-shnayim be-behema ve-rubo shel echad
kamohu*. And then it says רוב rov. אחד בעוף רוב rov שנים
בבהמה שחיטתו כשרה *rove echad be-of rove shnayim be-behema shechitanto kesheira*. So
the difference is that the beginning sounds like it's talking about לכתחילה
l'chatchilah *lechatchila*, השוחט *Hashochet*, you do this, and the end sounds like
it's a little bit בדיעבד bedi'avad *bedi'avad*. If you did the majority,
then it's valid. Sounds like it's בדיעבד bedieved *bedi'avad*, ideally we'd like
you to do more. So let's see what he says.
מדקתני השוחט *Mi-de-ktani Hashochet*, ואי סלקא דעתך רישא בקדשים *ve-ee salta da'atach
reisha be-kodshim*, המולק מיבעי ליה *hamolek mibaye lei*. So when it talks
about birds, it said השוחט *Hashochet*, it should have said המולק *Hamolek*.
The end of it doesn't have a verb, the end of it
just says majority is enough. But the beginning has a verb, so
it can't be talking about קדשים *Kodshim*, then it would have to
say המולק מיבעי ליה *Hamolek mibaye lei*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אלא מאי *ella mai*, so what do you want to say,
סיפא בקדשים *seifa be-kodshim*, שחיטתו כשרה *shechitanto kesheira*, it says the שחיטה
shechitah? *shechitah* is good. According to you, מליקתו כשרה מיבעי ליה *melikato
kesheira mibaye lei*, it should have said the מליקה *melika* is good.
הא לא קשיא *Ha lo kashya*, that's not difficult. איידי דסליק מבהמה
תני נמי שחיטתו כשרה *Aidi de-salik mi-behema tani nami shechitanto kesheira*. The
end, it talked about one by bird, two by בהמה behema, *behema*.
So the last thing it talked about was בהמה behemah *behema*, so
it could say שחיטה shechitah *shechitah* which is the right verb by
בהמה *behema*. אלא רישא *Ella reisha*, but the beginning, it started by
saying one by bird. The first thing it talked about was bird.
אלא רישא מכדי *Ella reisha michti*, let's take a look, אעוף קאי
*al of kai*, the first thing it mentions is bird. ואי סלקא
דעתך בקדשים *Ee salta da'atach be-kodshim*, המולק מיבעי ליה *Hamolek mibaye lei*,
it should have said המולק *Hamolek* not השוחט *Hashochet*. Okay, so that's
his דיוק *diyuk* about the use of the verb. רב שימי בר
אשי *Rav Shimi bar Ashi* אמר רישא בחולין *amar reisha be-chullin*, I'll
prove to you the first part is by חולין *Chullin* מהכא *me-hacha*,
דקתני אחד בעוף *de-ktani echad be-of*, shecht one by a bird. ואי
סלקא דעתך בקדשים *Ve-ee salta da'atach be-kodshim*, האיכא עולת העוף olat ha'of.
דבעי שני סימנים simanim, *ha-ika olas ha-of de-bai shnei simanim*, not all
birds are one. עולת העוף *Olas ha-of* you have to cut both
trachea and the esophagus as we've discussed in the past. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא מאי *ella mai*, so what do you
want to say, סיפא בקדשים *seifa be-kodshim*, the end is by קדשים
*Kodshim*? Still same problem, it says רוב אחד בעוף *rove echad be-of*,
the majority of one by a bird is enough. That's not true
about all birds. האיכא עולת העוף דבעי שני סימנים simanim, *Ha-ika olas
ha-of de-bai shnei simanim*, there's still the עולה olah *olah* that requires
two. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no no that I could
get out of, that I could say מאי רוב אחד *mai rove
echad*, what does it mean the majority of one by a bird?
It means רוב כל אחד ואחד *rove kol echad ve-echad*, it means
the majority of each one, meaning that and... ambiguous רוב אחד could
be read as the majority of just one of them, which is
true by the חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, or it could mean the
majority of each one, which is true by the עולת העוף. So
I could say that the end is talking about קרבנות korbanot and
it's framed it in a way that could allow for reading the
bird as either one or two because some birds are one some
birds are two. ובדין הוא דליתני רוב שנים, u'vedin hu d'litni rov
shnayim, and it really should have said the majority of both by
the bird, אבל כיוון דאיכא חטאת דסגי ליה בחד סימן, aval keivan
d'ika chatat d'sagi lei b'chad siman, but since there are the חטאת
chatat bird that one סימן siman is enough, משום הכי לא פסיקא
ליה, mishum hachi lo psika lei, therefore it didn't say the majority
of two. So his answer is if we're talking about sacrifices sometimes
you need two. The beginning says you only have to שחט shacht
one by a bird so clearly it's not sacrifices, but the framing
at the end, the majority of one could be read either way.
It could be read to say the majority of one or the
majority of each one and it framed it in that ambiguous way
to include two types of birds, the עולה bird and the חטאת
chatat bird. Okay. רב פפא אמר רישא בחולין מהא. Rav Pappa amar
reisha b'chullin meha.
So they're all saying the same thing but different ways of inferring
it. The beginning is חולין from the following, דתני רבי יהודה אומר
עד שישחוט את הורידין, d'tani Rabbi Yehuda omer ad she'yishchot et ha'vridin,
that you... ah now we get to the blood issue again and
where the blood issue really matters which is the cutting of the
ורידין vridin again, let's assume it means the jugular vein. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you have to שחט shacht the jugular vein
ופליגי רבנן עליה u'pligi rabanan aleih and the Rabbis argue. So let's
talk about this. Does it really make sense to argue about that
by קדשים when you need the blood? So אי אמרת בשלמא בחולין,
ei amrat bishlama b'chullin, if they're talking about
non-sacrifices שפיר, shapir, I understand why there's a debate if you cut
the jugular vein, אלא אי אמרת בקדשים, ela ei amrat b'kodashim, but
if we're talking about sacrifices, אמאי פליגי רבנן עליה, amai pligi rabanan
aleih, why would the Rabbis ever argue with רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
Of course you need to שחט shacht the jugular vein, you need
to get out the blood. הוא עצמו לדמו הוא צריך, hu atzmo
l'damo hu tzarich, your whole point is to get out the blood.
So very nice that actually the גמרא Gemara this was raised yesterday,
right, and sort of goes to the point David was saying before
what's the point of the שחיטה? shechita To technically make the animal
כשר kosher or to get out the blood? So by sacrifices it's
actually both but the blood is obviously a central thing, you know,
the goal is to get blood. Also you have to do a
כשר שחיטה. kosher shechitah. So here the גמרא Gemara is actually saying
that רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda idea of cutting the vein everybody would
agree that that's a requirement by sacrifices with the focus on with
the focus on getting the blood. So the beginning where it's debated
is not talking about sacrifices. Okay. רב אשי אמר סיפא בקדשים
מהא. Rav Ashi amar seifa b'kodashim meha. I will prove,
I agree with you, but I'm going to focus on the end
and prove the end is about sacrifices from the following case דתני
השוחט שני ראשים כאחד שחיטתו כשרה. d'tani hashochet shenei rashim k'echad shechitato
k'sherah. Now this is really not the משנה Mishnah we read but
the next משנה Mishna coming up. השוחט שני ראשים כאחד שחיטתו כשרה.
Hashochet shenei rashim k'echad shechitato k'sherah.
If you slaughter two heads at once you got your two animals
lined side by side and you got your super long knife and
you slice both of their throats with one movement, okay? That's going
to be the משנה Mishna coming up very soon. So that's going
on the last case and that says if you do it it's
valid. So it says השוחט דיעבד אין לכתחילה לא, hashochet di'avad in
l'chatchilah lo, if you שחט shechted it is כשר, kasher, means that
it's only good דיעבד. di'avad. So why is that true? אי אמרת
בשלמא בקדשים, ei amrat bishlama b'kodashim, if it's
sacrifices היינו דלכתחילה לא, hainu d'l'chatchilah lo, then I understand why לכתחילה
l'chatchila you're not supposed to do
it משום דתני רב יוסף mishum d'tani Rav Yosef because רב יוסף
Rav Yosef taught תזבח, tizbach, it says, you know, it says by
the sacrifices it says תזבחוהו, tizbachuhu, you shall slaughter it, לרצונכם תזבחוהו,
l'rtzonchem tizbachuhu, for your desire you should slaughter these sacrifices. So it
says, so we make the following דרשה. drasha. תזבח, tizbach, you shall
slaughter, שלא יהיו שנים שוחטים זבח אחד, shelo yihyu shnayim shochtim zevach
echad, you should not have two people doing the שחיטה shechita, at
the same time for one animal.
תזבחוהו, tizbachuhu, you shall slaughter it, the הו hu means it the
one animal, שלא יהא אחד שוחט שני זבחים, shelo yehei echad shochet
shenei zevachim, one person should only שחט shacht one animal not two.
So we have this idea that and that's a פסוק pasuk by
קרבנות. korbanot. So by קרבנות korbanot it should only be one person
שחט shachting one, not two doing one and not one doing two.
Now there's a little problem with that דרשה drasha by the way
because תזבחוהו tizbachuhu is in the plural. You plural should שחט shacht
it. So how do we learn it to say that one person
only one person should שחט shacht one animal? So it says it's
in the plural so ואמר רב כהנא תזבחהו כתיב v'amar Rav Kahana
tizbachahu ktiv because the first ו vav is not actually written. So
though while we read it with a ו vav you plural, it's
written in a way that would read you singular שחט shacht it
and therefore it's only one person.
So what's the תזבחוהו tizbachuhu coming to teach you?
So the so the lacking of the ו vav is teaching you
only one person should שחט shacht not two people שחט shacht at
the same time, and the הו hu it is only שחט shacht
one animal not שחט shacht two animals at the same time. And
this is a פסוק pasuk by קרבנות. korbanot. So so therefore we
understand why the משנה Mishna would be saying that דיעבד di'avad it's
good, only דיעבד di'avad because it's שחט shachting two animals and that's
only דיעבד di'avad by קרבנות. korbanot. אלא אי אמרת בחולין, ela ei
amrat b'chullin, but if you're talking about
non-sacrifices אפילו לכתחילה נמי, afilu l'chatchilah nami, there is no there should
be no problem to שחט shacht two animals at the same time.
At least in principle. ואף ריש לקיש סבר רישא בחולין סיפא בקדשים,
v'af Reish Lakish savar reisha b'chullin seifa b'kodashim, and we could also
infer this from ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, דאמר ריש לקיש מאחר ששנינו
רוב d'amar Reish Lakish me'achar she'shaninu rov Since the beginning of the
משנה Mishna says a majority suffices, למה שנינו רוב אחד בעוף ורוב
שנים בבהמה, lama shaninu rov echad be'of verov shenayim bebehema, why does
the end of the משנה Mishna repeat and say the majority of
one by עוף of and two by a בהמה, saying the same
thing? לפי ששנינו, Lefi sheshaninu, because we taught by יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, הביאו לו את התמיד, hevi'u lo et hatamid, they brought the
תמיד tamid to the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. צירצו, Tzirtzo, he שחט shacht it, which is a funny word
but it means he שחט shacht it, ומירק אחר שחיטתו, umireik achar
shechitato, and another person finished the שחיטה shechita for him על ידו.
al yado. So therefore it says if somebody finishes the שחיטה, shechita
he did the majority, somebody else finished. That's what it says by
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So יכול
לא מירק יהא פסול, yacho lo mireik yei pasul, I might think
that by קרבנות korbanot if you didn't finish it would be invalid,
maybe majority doesn't suffice by קרבנות korbanot because we have this משנה
by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Therefore, לכך שנינו, l'kach shaninu, therefore the
משנה says at the end רוב אחד בעוף ורוב שנים בבהמה, rov
echad be'of verov shenayim bebehema, that a majority is enough to tell
you again that even by sacrifices a majority is enough. אמר מר,
Amar mar, so now let's just finish up this point. יכול לא
מירק יהא פסול, yacho lo mireik yei pasul, I might have thought
that if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol did not finish it or
somebody did not finish it for him it would be invalid, maybe
you needed to do the full amount by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So the גמרא Gemara says אם כן הויא לה עבודה באחר. im
kein havelay avoda be'acher.
How could that be? How could I think that you need to
finish it? If you needed to finish it and somebody else was
doing it for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, all of the service can only be done by the כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the fact that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
lets somebody else finish it proves that the finishing is not central,
is not really required, because if the finishing were required nobody else
could do it. דתניא, De'tanya, we taught, what?
די בכל לכתחילה לא. dei ba'kol l'chatchila lo. What's לכתחילה לא? l'chatchila
lo? That
means that you shouldn't, what was
that?
No, two at the one time. דתניא, De'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, כל עבודת יום הכפורים אינן כשרות אלא בו, kol avodat
yom hakippurim einam k'sherot ella bo, all of the acts of service
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur is only with the כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's
the point: יכול יהא פסול מדרבנן. yacho yei pasul midirabbanan. Clearly I
couldn't have thought that it was biblically required, because if so we
would not have let another person who wasn't the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol do it. But maybe at least rabbinically by sacrifices you have
to finish, since it's only rabbinic we'll let somebody else do it,
but maybe it's at least a rabbinic requirement. דסלקא דעתך אמינא, Desalka
daitach amina, I might have thought איכא פסול מדרבנן, ikka psul midirabbanan,
there's a rabbinic problem by sacrifices if you don't do the full
amount. לכך שנינו, L'kach shaninu, therefore we said רוב אחד בעוף ורוב
שנים בבהמה, rov echad be'of verov shenayim bebehema,
that it repeats the משנה that says a majority is enough, which
means a majority is enough whether biblically, whether rabbinically, whether by חולין,
whether by sacrifices. In all cases you don't have to do more
than a majority. So the גמרא Gemara says ומאחר דאפילו פסולה דרבנן
ליכא, ume'achar de'afillu psula de'rabbanan leika, since there's not even a rabbinic
invalidity, למה לי למרק? lama li lemareik? So why do we bother
having somebody finish in the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol case? So the
גמרא Gemara. says מצוה למרק. mitzva lemareik. No, because it's not like
it's invalid rabbinically but it's still an ideal. So there's an ideal
at least by קרבנות korbanot to do it completely. Okay, now does
that ideal translate also into non-קרבנות? korbanot? That was an issue that
got raised at the beginning of the גמרא when we say a
majority is enough, do we mean it's enough בדיעבד Bedi'eved. or לכתחילה
Lechatchila you should do it all? And that was sort of left
unresolved. As I said, and we're about to hear in a minute,
by birds anyway the whole question about שחיטה shechita the jugular vein,
שחיטה shechita the majority, שחיטה shechita only one, in practice we just
basically decapitate the bird. So we cut off everything, both סימנים, simanim.
all the veins and whatever, all these issues are moot. Okay, but
at least in principle here what we said is that even by
קרבנות korbanot and even rabbinically majority suffices,
and whether there's a מצוה mitzva or an ideal to do it
all by קרבנות, korbanot, yes, by non-קרבנות korbanot it's a little unclear.
But what we have seen is now, and I'm going to turn
it over to Aaron in a minute, we've seen now the basic
principles about two by mammals, one by bird, none by fish. There's
a debate if the one by bird is biblical or rabbinic. The
majority suffices. We have yet to see conceptually if the majority is
because it's like it's all or just the majority alone suffices, which
might be part of the question of ideally you should do all.
We have seen the debate if fifty percent counts as the majority,
right? Whether that is a universal question, is fifty percent like a
majority, or it's a more local question. What are we defining? Are
we defining which criteria are we defining so that the fifty percent
falls on the other side? Okay, and right, so those are like
the major issues and that it doesn't matter whether it's חולין or
sacrifices, although we did see that by sacrifices because you need the
blood, although you don't have to שחט shacht more of the סימנים,
simanim. you have to make sure to שחט, shacht, to cut the
jugular vein in order to get out the blood because of the
centrality of blood. So we're going to stop here with the שיעור
shiur and ask Aaron Braund, Aaron why don't you come sit over
here, grab a chair or something, who is about to receive his
קבלה kabbala in שחיטה shechita. and has been studying for the last
few months in terms of this to, did you bring some knives?
I'm not sure how much you're on
דף כ"ח.
daf chaf chet. כ"ח. chaf chet. Okay. We haven't done טריפות treifos
yet.
Okay. So I don't know how much you all know or what
you're curious about, so I'll guess
I'll
take questions at some point. But it's interesting listening to you speak
about the דף daf and the הלכה halacha found in the גמרא
because a lot of it, although is הלכה, halacha, we don't exactly
follow. For instance, fifty percent when you're actually שחט'ן shechting is not
רוב. You have to have a noticeable רוב to the point that
most hold you can't measure. There's a small group that does have
a means of measuring, which the שמלה חדשה, Simla Chadasha, which is
the main work on שחיטה shechita that people read to learn the
הלכות halachos of שחיטה. shechita. There's a small group that does measure.
But generally practice we don't measure. So you have to have, he
states, the majority which is seeable is about sixty percent.
So there are a number of other nuances which I guess we
can sort of wait till you ask about. But I actually brought
the closest thing I could find in my house to a chicken.
Just
to show you, well, hopefully not, because then my son would be
pretty mad.
But just to show you sort of what it looks like. Because
for me when I started learning, the biggest, I guess the biggest
piece that was not in the books and you really couldn't read
anywhere was how you do it. How you hold it.
Yeah. So I guess I can show you as best I can
with the teddy bear what it looks like for a chicken, which
is what it looks like for most small birds.
It's a little different for big birds because you need multiple people
to hold the bird. Am I being broadcasted? All right.
So this is the חלף, chalaf, which I'm sure you've heard about.
It's square on the ends. Now in America it's made out of
raw metals
and is fairly simple. In Israel they get very fancy with them
because it's more of a business. In Israel you almost can never
find them in the raw metal, which is like the non-reflective very
plain looking. They're always shined, which is more of the חסידיש Chassidic
מנהג minhag to shine them. They also put...
Where does that all come from, shining versus raw?
I think it has to do with just the idea of how
smooth it is, like the עיקור ikur and whether you're tearing or
it's pausing at all.
הלכה halachically there's no difference. But some people like a shinier, nicer
knife.
Here this is a fiber handle, which is how they're mostly made
in America, at least as I can find, versus in Israel they
have them like Cutco knives, you know, that plastic shape and molded.
The tang goes all the way through, which you can sort of
see here but it's filled in. It has to go through not
all the way to the butt of the knife, but enough that
when you're holding the knife you're holding by the tang and not
just by the handle. So if you ever thought of using a
Nakiri knife, which is a Japanese knife that looks a lot like
this, usually the prohibiting factor is the tang doesn't go through or
it's too heavy.
Because if you're not holding by the metal, then the concern is
that it won't be straight?
The knife has to be one piece.
So by holding here, you're holding in one piece. I mean the,
this isn't considered part of the knife, the handle isn't.
So do you sharpen it like after every שחיטה shechita, or after
every...
It doesn't need after every שחיטה. shechita It needs to be checked
before and after each שחיטה, shechita because we don't really hold by
חזקות chazakas at all.
Even for the first פרק stuff we did?
Yeah. If you end up in a real bad situation right before
שבת, Shabbos, there are some, there are a few that you can
rely on, but we almost never, especially today, rely on them because
food is so prevalent and most people aren't doing this in their
homes.
So how often were you told to show it to a
חכם?
Chacham? That's a good question. We were never...
Never discussed showing it to a חכם? Chacham?
No. In the beginning...
I don't want to be put
in חרם!
cherem! I don't have קבלה kabbalah yet. So in the beginning every
single time he has to check before and after. At first he
was checking before us, and now he's sort of insisted it's our
knives... or he was checking after us. Now he's insisted it's our
knives, he'll check it first, but we're the ones who have to
decide on it. So we check... How do you check it?
So there again this is where הלכה halacha and the שמלה חדשה
simlah hadashah and modern practice differ quite a bit. You're supposed to
check it 12 times. It has three edges: it has the side,
the actual blade, and the other side and you're supposed to check
twice
with your nail on each edge and twice with the meat of
your finger and never checking both at the same time. Some people
tell you that they check with the finger and the nail at
the same time, you can't do that.
That's one thing that everybody agrees is not okay. You have to
do one at a time. Now in America and for most people
as far as I know, they don't use their fingers anymore. It's
just not done. What about the nail and finger?
Do they do the tongue test?
The tongue test is done, but that's not, yeah, the tongue test
we were taught how to do the tongue, but that's not, you're
not like checking the whole knife with your tongue. The tongue is
only if you think you might, these knives are so sharp and
I'm happy to pass it around if you're all very careful with
it if you want to check it yourself,
but the tongue test is only, these knives are incredibly smooth and
sharp
and if you feel like you've got a place where you're slow
and you're not sure if it's a פגימה pegimah because slowness doesn't
טריף treif whatever you've done. So especially after you've done שחיטה shechita
and you're checking to make sure that it didn't get a פגימה,
pegimah, tell me if there's a word here you don't know, otherwise
I'm assuming that you've seen these. But if you end up with
a פגימה pegimah in the knife based on you hit some stone
that was wedged in the skin or something, so the שחיטה shechita.
would not be good because it happened before you cut the סימנים.
simanim So when you're checking, if you feel a little slowness and
you're not entirely sure and it's hard, there are a number of
different ways that you can check. One is you can hold it
up to the sun and look, which actually is not what they're
describing when they say hold it up to the sun, I found
out based on this book. A lot of people will hold it
up to the sun and look at it and you can actually
see better, but that's not what they're describing. What they're describing is
holding it up to the sun and looking at the shadow.
רש״י Rashi has both explanations.
Oh yeah? Okay. So because shadows magnify, you can see the little
indent better on the shadow than you can on the actual knife
looking. I've actually never done that, I don't know if that really
works, in theory it sounds great. The other option is running water
down the blade, you'll see that the stream changes where the פגימה
pegimah is. And if you don't have either of those options, and
if you have a very clean knife I hope,
you can hold it to your tongue and actually taste it differently.
It's sort of like if you've ever, if you've ever used
a metal fork and had a takeout meal where there's aluminum and
you touch the fork to the aluminum and you taste the fork
and it's got that like metallic bitter taste, so it tastes about
like that. It's not quite as strong, but you get that taste.
When you check the sides you only mean the tip where it
starts angling in, right?
Yeah, you're not like checking here, no no no. The way you
check is basically to go like this, you go in each direction,
just like at the edge, right at the
edge at the edge and then spin to the top and then
spin to the other top the other side. I actually had, it's
worthwhile checking the sides, not that I needed to say that, but
because I had a little scratch on the side of the blade
that was actually I couldn't feel on the top, but was catching
pretty hard on the side and when I handed it to the
guy who's teaching us he could actually feel it on the top
as well which would be עקור. ikur.
You have a sharpener in your little kit?
Yeah, we use a whetstone.
Yeah, we use a whetstone. There are a number of different
הלכות halachot
or מנהגים minhagim
when it comes to how you sharpen and things of that nature.
Pull down the
bird there.
This is known as the green stone. They actually oddly enough don't
do grit. Like if you go to non-Jewish sources for whetstones and
things like that, they'll tell you the best thing is a stone
that uses oil. You can't do that for a שחיטה shechitah knife
because the oil gets in the פגימה pegimah and you can't feel
it, so it has to be a water-based stone. And they'll tell
you grit, they don't really do that in שחיטה. shechitah You ask
for the green stone, which is...
Is that slate though, is it?
I really don't know what it's made of because all they describe
it as is the green stone and I'm fairly certain if I
ask they'll say it's a green stone. It's just sort of they
import it and...
There's a rock called greenstone.
Yeah, so that might be that might be what it is, I
really don't know, but this is the one you use most often
once you get a sharp knife. This knife probably has about 50
hours of sharpening in it. This is used to get it smooth
and these are used to shape it. So this is the coarsest
and the next coarsest, so you guys can pass these around.
What is a whetstone?
So it's just a stone that we use to sharpen.
Why is it called whet?
Oh I think it's from shape.
Oh
it means to sharpen.
To whet your appetite, sharpen, not W-E-T.
Sorry,
so one side is...
So when you're first using the knife, when you get the knife,
it's
really...
Why don't you get the knife sharpened in the first place?
This knife is paper thin. If I cut paper with it, it'll
put a פגימה pigimah in it. Wow. It is really so sharp
it's amazing. In fact, the case they gave us guaranteed every single
time gave us a פגימה, pigimah, so I had to make a
different case for it so it wouldn't actually touch the blade. This
sort of hovers inside the case.
It is so sharp that if they spent 50 hours sharpening it,
by the time they gave it to us it would be junk.
I bought this from a guy in Brooklyn and he had a
cardboard box with just knives clanked all over the place. So just
because it's not you just look in you find the knife that
appeals to you and then you've got to do the work.
Did the knife pick the wizard? I'm sorry?
I tried that.
There are those who- I'm sorry.
You said if you cut paper it would be a פגימה pigimah
but if you cut an animal, won't? Correct.
How's that? It's interesting. It's probably not that the paper actually causes
a פגימה. pigimah. It's mostly likely that the fibers get stuck in
the knife, which is a huge deal.
These knives, especially because of the amount of times they're rubbed against
things, have a very strong static current to them... or not current,
what am I looking for? Static, yeah, charge, thank you. So that
when you cut paper with them- and we had to practice on
paper before we got into actual chicken- you get all the fibers
sort of stuck on it and it takes a long time to
get them off. You actually before and after each שחיטה shechitah strop
it so that you get all the fibers off of it.
The other thing that we do to check the knife which isn't
talked about very often, in fact, the שמלה חדשה Simlah Chadashah doesn't
even give you a way to do it, is how sharp the
knife is.
And so we do it like that based- and please don't try
this yourself because you will cut yourself.
But you put it on just a pulled part of the skin
here and you can feel how many layers of skin it pulls.
Wow. And so if it pulls two or more, it's sharp. If
it pulls less, it's not.
Do you use chickens and בהמות behemot with the same knife?
No. This knife is too small for בהמות. behemot.
For בהמות, behemot, they're about- it depends. It has to be the
length
of the neck.
It has to be twice the width
unless you go back and forth.
Right.
So we generally hold twice the size of the neck. And the
custom today, which is very peculiar, is they're getting bigger and bigger.
Like a chicken's knife used to be about this big. It's now
this big. It made our שוחט shochet a little uncomfortable because one
of the big issues with שחיטה Shechitah is דריסה, derisah, which is
pressing down, and the heavier the knife, the more likely you're doing
דריסה. derisah. So that's why you actually can't use a בהמה's knife
for a chicken. That's why we have specific knives. So for like
דקות dakot and turkeys it's about this big, and for בהמות behemot
it's really about that big.
Are you studying for בהמות behemot also?
Not yet. I'd like to learn דקות, dakot, but
גסות gasot is not- butcher cows- isn't really relevant as I can't
afford to buy a cow, nor do I have the machinery to
flip it upside down. Right. Let's- yeah.
So I'll do it without the knife because to do all this
you put the knife in your mouth and I can't talk and
do that at the same time. Or as our שוחט shochet would
say, you do it with the hilt of the knife in your
mouth. Why do you put the
knife in
your mouth?
So I'll show you and you'll sort of see. One of the
issues with doing שחיטה Shechitah is that the שוחט shochet is responsible
for all the pain and suffering that the animal feels. And
so you have to be very careful that you do this quickly
and efficiently and that you don't hurt the animal. Not to mention
that if you break a limb it's no longer כשר. kosher. So
you have to be very, very careful. This is for all purposes
today our chicken and it does actually look a bit like a
chicken when you pull it like this. Try to get past the
fact that it looks like I'm torturing a bear, but the legs
are directly below. The animal, about a yearling, is about this size,
maybe a little bit bigger with the feathers. Head a little smaller
and neck a little longer. But this is how it naturally sits.
So when we pick it up you need two hands. First of
all because you have to layer the wings.
We hold- yeah, we have to hold the bird a certain way
first so you can hold it with one hand, and the other
is so that the bird calms down. We don't stun animals before
we kill them, so they have to be basically as naturally sedated
as possible. And so this way which is great, it's a great
just a handed down tradition of how to basically debilitate a bird
in a humane way. I found fascinating the first time I saw
it and if you ever get to see it it's pretty cool
because the bird will struggle like crazy until it's held and then
it just goes limp, goes completely limp. So what we do is
we take the- the right wing and put it over the left
wing like this and the bird actually its joints shift a little
bit so they get in there fairly easily and then you put
your left hand below the wings in the armpits and the bird
is actually at this point because you press down a little bit
fairly calm the place where it starts to squawk a little bit
is when you do this part so you have to be very
quick you grab the skin from the back of the head and
you pinch it with your other fingers which is again why you
can see you need two hands you can't do this with one
hand and you end up there's a lot of skin here so
you pull it back and then you flip the bird very quickly
and the bird just goes completely limp at this point
and you try to afterwards if you haven't already which hopefully you
have because you're trying to do this as quick as possible
you pull the skin from the back of the head and the
neck and you end up with a bird which is completely limp
on the back of your hand and the head sort of separates
out like this and you end up with all the feathers separating
and just a red zone right here which is exactly where you
do the שחיטה shechita.
so then you take the knife out of your mouth you say
the ברכה Bracha and a quick הולכה והובאה Holacha Vehava'ah an out
and back motion.
Is the knife is it at an angle or exactly parallel to
the ground and to the...
Yeah when you when you pull the knife out it should be
directly up and down it should be perpendicular and we actually don't
most people hold a knife like this or like this there's הלכה
Halacha that you can't do that because it causes דריסה Derisa
so I've been told that my hand is a little weird because
I put the finger way out there but you're supposed to hold
it like that so my hand just sort of pushes the finger
out but you hold it this way you do a...
but it's not a... it is at a slight angle.
What do you mean?
It's not exactly like that it's at a little bit of an
angle
the way you were holding
it the way you were holding it. Oh! So you try to
go perpendicular I guess it's hard to
see
at a perfect angle but you you do the cut which generally
at that point if you so you try to go as fast
as possible because really if you're going to kill something you want
it to be quick also because you want a הולכה והובאה Holacha
Vehava'ah and if you go really slow I've found you can't do
that because you'll get... we were very nervous in the beginning and
so so going forward if you went slow the bird would start
to jump up and down and then you've got to pull away.
So if you go very quickly the bird doesn't move at all.
You put the knife back in your mouth which I won't do
again this time. Bird blood? It actually doesn't have blood generally unless
you are slow or you
wiggle which you shouldn't do.
You really don't get much blood at all. The blood comes at
this part which is when you have to check that there was
no עיקור הסימנים Ikur Hasimanim and that you've actually done a כשר
Kosher cut. You push on what's called the שיפוי הכובע Shipui Hako'va
which is the little triangle you have here. Right by the chin
essentially? Yeah right under your chin bone birds also have that below
their beak and so you push there and towards the cut and
the קנה Kaneh the trachea pops right out
if you've done it right. If you've not done it right it
doesn't.
But if you've done it right it pops right out and then
you grab the bird carefully because the legs move at this point
and they're very very sharp. Their toes are like nails so you
go from the side and then we put it into a device
which holds it upside down until it bleeds out. Self-hanging?
We actually don't put it in a hanger. It's a cone? Yeah
we put it in a very sophisticated שחיטה shechita device known as
a traffic cone.
It should be published. That's okay. But it's in it's basically in
a giant...
you cut both the trachea and esophagus?
I was always told that's not the case that that nowadays we
cut the trachea and the esophagus. So you try.
You try. The esophagus the you try for both. You're always trying
for both. There's a very fine window with chickens of where you
can go because you can't cut the spine. If you cut the
spine it's considered as if you did דריסה Derisa because you got
too far down.
You can you can get into the spine but you can't actually
cut the spine itself.
It's very it's very nuanced to try to find where that is.
You have to know on your knife how far to go and
you can't push at all so you've got to know how fast
and how far to go to not go too far. And the
esophagus is behind the trachea? The esophagus is it's funny when the
bird is alive and and normal the esophagus because it's soft and
it's long meaning it's longer than the distance it travels usually falls
in front of the trachea which is what you'll see in the
pictures here.
However when you pull everything
back because it's soft and the קנה Kaneh is not soft and
is the right length when you pull everything back the קנה Kaneh
pops up as far as it can because it doesn't want to
move whereas the the the esophagus will travel behind.
And so, when you cut through, you get through the esophagus, through
the קנה, kana, the trachea first,
and it's hard, and so it's easier to measure if you've done
half of that. Just more than half of that, 60% of that
is כשר. kosher. You're aiming to get all of it, but when
you push on the שיפוע הכובע, shipua hakova, the esophagus is not
coming out. It's very soft.
I don't know what to relate it to. I mean it's a
tissue, I mean it's very very soft.
How about blood vessels? Are you so are you cutting the jugular
vein or the carotid?
So there's so if you cut those if you cut those it's
ideal. You have to cut those for the bird to be כשר.
kosher. We hold that if you don't cut them while the bird
is still alive... To cut what? To cut the veins and the
arteries.
But were you told the vein or the artery? The jugular vein
or the carotid artery?
We weren't, we were told there's a blood vessel. Okay, fine. We
work with blood vessel. Okay fine. If you don't cut them, the
blood doesn't come out and we hold that if the blood doesn't
come out while the bird is alive, then you can't כשר, kosher,
meaning even putting salt on it will not bring the blood out.
So you have to cut those. However, that's not שחיטה. shechita? Right.
שחיטה shechita is cutting the סימנים. simanim So it is addressed in
the שמלה חדשה Simlah Chadashah and it's legitimate to think that at
some point you might end up cutting the סימנים simanim, and not
the the veins and and arteries and that's still כשר. kosher. You
just have to cut them afterwards so that they...
While it's still pumping.
While it's still alive. Yeah. If you if you cut, you push,
you don't see anything, you've got to you've got to nick them.
Have when when you've done it, does it always come together like
just naturally? The vessels with the שחיטה?
shechita, It's a good question. It's hard to tell because at at
times when we push... I would say generally yes. However, I've had
cuts where nothing has happened until I pushed on the שיפוע הכובע
shipua hakova and then it's like a struggle to get the trachea
out because the cut was so small and and then they've popped.
So it's hard to tell if they were done by עיקור, ikur,
meaning the...
But they're done by your pressure then.
Yeah. The סימנים simanim were certainly כשר kosher and the bird was
כשר. kosher. Whether the whether the veins popped because I was pressing
on it or not, not so clear.
Have you ever had a bird that that defied the usual behavior
and when you had its wings or whatever...
No, we've had שוחטים shochtim defy the usual הלכה. halacha. We have
not, no, just generally if you hold the תפיסה tfisa right, it's
not moving. The תפיסה tfisa is the whole thing.
And about how many of these have you done?
I have done, I mean of varying ages. They're all different. Most
recently I did a rooster which is tremendously different.
Around a dozen, around a dozen over the four to six months
that we've been doing this.
When do you determine whether it's alive? I'm sorry, usually one of
the chickens?
Only
chicken.
We have only done chickens, hens, and roosters at this point. We're,
he's arranging geese and ducks. Oh, turkey?
We've not done turkey.
How do you determine whether when it stops being alive? You said
it has to be alive when you cut the veins.
So, it's interesting. It's for chickens it happens so quickly, it's pretty
it's pretty rapid. You can tell by פרכוס, pirkus, which are the
the death rattle, which we don't require in healthy animals,
or healthy birds at least.
It's a good question. I mean it's been very clear for us,
so we haven't really discussed it in depth, and I don't remember
him פסקנינג paskening exactly when the animal is dead.
Well, I'm sorry, because שחיטה shechita, is considered actually dead. So when
you say it's still alive, it kind of...
at least הלכתית halachically though, right? It's not, it's not, because there's
the issue of אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, and I think
what you're referring to is for a Jew after you cut, after
you
do
שחיטה, shechita you can actually cut off the bird, which we don't
actually do. We פסקן pasken that you can't do because for non-Jews
it's not dead yet. Even if you do שחיטה, shechita. for a
non-Jew, it's not dead yet. They have to wait until the פרכוס
pirkus is finished.
Dissected but not dead?
Exactly. So it's technically ready to eat once you cut it, but
it's not dead. So you have to wait until it's actually its
heart stops beating and the פרכוס... pirkus...
And that's when you cut the other veins while still the heart's
beating and whatever it is and you haven't done
it already.
Right. So you preferably you've done it already. If you look up
שחיטה shechitah? online you'll find a bunch of PETA or Peta YouTube
videos about Rubashkin's because they visited undercover their facility and actually saw
them cutting the veins afterwards and thought it was inhumane, but it's
something you can see.
And you'll see the cow mooing after שחיטה. shechitah?
Yeah,
it's not actually mooing, it's huffing, which is okay.
No, it's a different reaction.
It's the same way that if you kill a person that way
the air releases and it makes a noise. It's not it's not
actually mooing. The thing is you're so careful about... getting the cut
precise that they're not really worried about the veins and everything and
for a cow you're not pushing everything forward you're grabbing the קנה
kaneh and cutting and so you're grabbing from the front and cutting
and so it's very likely that the veins and arteries will move
to the back and you won't end up cutting them but you
don't want to keep cutting because you want to do it in
the proper motion and the least pain to the animal so then
once that happens if the animal's not bleeding out fast enough you
don't want it to suffer so they go in with a small
knife and they cut the it's very quick but it doesn't doesn't
look great if you're used to non-kosher slaughter where they just do
it all very quickly.
Do they teach גויים Goyim to do שחיטה?
shechitah
They can't. I mean you could teach them how it's done but
ultimately because it comes from the
Jews. Yeah only the Jews. Only those commanded.
What is the ברכה bracha you say?
אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על השחיטה. Asher kidshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu al hashechitah.
You do it with every chicken?
No you do it before you start a session. You don't you
don't do it each and every time. You have the כוונה kavannah
that anything that's brought to you will be under this ברכה bracha
and I intend to שחט shacht and so you make the ברכה
bracha and then you then you go through it and as long
as there's not a interruption you're still fine.
So as soon as an animal or bird is שחט shechted uh-huh
we could eat it.
You could. It would be as as the גמרא that we learned
from said many times it would be hard by a chicken because
it's dead by the time you cut it off much less cooked
it or soaked salted I mean you've got an hour and a
half at least of soaking and salting and then you've got to
cook it it's just not it's not going to happen even if
you roasted it you grilled it it's still going to be an
hour.
So my question was concerning the idea that it's not dead for
a non-Jew but there's a statement in גמרא in סנהדרין Sanhedrin says
there's nothing that is permitted to Jews is prohibited to non-Jews.
Right so that is why we don't do it. Oh okay. It
says I mean the שמלה חדשה Simla Chadasha says very plainly we
don't want to be less פרום frum than them and so therefore
we don't do it.
Personal question what was your personal reaction the first and second time
you went through this process? It had to be very difficult.
It should have been however because I didn't grow up in a...
I didn't grow up פרום frum and I worked on farms and
I had done this before but not כשר. kosher.
I had not done chickens. Chickens was a first. I think for
us it was for the guys who went through this with me
it's for some of us it's sort of considering the fact that
you're about to take a life. I think for a lot of
us it's just you're so nervous about what you're about to do
like trying to get it right you've got somebody who is a
professional a מומחה mumcheh standing right behind you sort of just concerned
that you're going to mess something up and luckily for all of
us every single one of us every chicken we've done has been
כשר kosher which is the first time he's said he's taught this
and that's happened but it's also you create a lot of nerves
every time you do it cause you don't want to be that
guy. Did you eat some of your own שחיטה? shechitah Yes yeah
you have to.
Is it a lot fresher?
It tastes substantially different. Better? Yeah because chickens that are produced by
places like Rubashkin's Perdue anywhere spray it down with an edible what
am I looking for preservative and you get a lot of that
in the taste. The other difference is that we're eating it a
lot sooner.
I mean so fresh. So fresh. It's a lot fresher it's also
a little younger. Listen
you become so accustomed to what chicken tastes like that you probably
will just be like it's different. My parents when I gave them
some from the first chicken I did said it tasted like שווארמה.
shawarma.
So gamey maybe?
A little?
I think it's just has more it's less dried out because it's
sat in a package less.
How do the גויים Goyim do the שחט shechting of the chicken?
It's
as far as chickens it's substantially different as far as cows it's
like captive bolt?
Usually it's they you pick up the chicken by the legs as
opposed to nicely and by the back of the wings you just
pick it up and clamp it into a there's a belt that
runs a metal thing and it clamps the foot and the chicken
hangs upside down and it goes up and then into a ridiculously
hot bath that has an electric charge. So
the electric charge kills them immediately but the hot bath that it
sits in for about 30 seconds as it moves takes all the
feathers off so it's a very efficient process. For cattle the way
they do it is they just put them in a in a
Temple Grandin yeah they put them in a closed-in chute
who was on the farms where I was coming from Champaign Illinois
wow yeah she studied at Champaign so you put them in a
closed chute basically and then I've actually I just saw recently that
they now have it so it's a loose gun it used to
be that you put them in a... In a chute in a
stall, close the door behind them and then press a button and
an alarm sounds, like an errrr, and then there's a piston that
shoots into the head and the animal just had its head held
there. And that's the only difference between שחיטה shechitah and, besides the
quality of the knife and how careful you are. Now they actually
get them while they're walking through with a pull-down gun which is
on a chain up above and it pulls down like a dog
leash and they just press it and then put it
back and wham.
It doesn't kill it. That's the whole point. It can't kill. It
stuns it. It stuns it.
Then how do they kill it?
So they cut it. They still cut it with a knife. You
have to cut it here because these are the largest veins in
the animal and you need the heart alive because the heart has
to pump out the blood. Because otherwise you just can't get it
out.
What is the gun? Is it electric stun?
I don't know this new pull-down one. It used to be a
piston, it used to be just like a banging and then a
bolt. It was a sharp metal bolt that came out of a
piston, built up pressure, you press the button it released and cracked
the skull and hit the nervous system at the back of the
brain. The brain on a cow is very small, you can see
from there it's really tiny so it pierces and goes back and
hits the
nervous system at the back of the brain. But then someone is
standing there if not kosher in the regular...
The one I saw was a pull-down thing, they were still walking
afterwards which was very confusing.
No, no, but someone's then taking a knife and it's not like
an electric blade that they use?
No, no, someone still does because the animal moves too.
Other than
checking the knife and the סימנים, which is the פסול psul when
you have to be most sensitive to דריסה, drisah, right, pressure?
Right. So the moniker, the סימן siman that they use is אשיח"ד,
Ashi Chad,
which is עיקור, ikor, שהייה, shehiyah, הגרמה, hagramah, חלדה, chaladah, and
דריסה. drisah.
Right. So now you know what the פסולים psulim are but
I'm saying which of the ones by
practice you have to really...
every single one of them. שהייה, Shehiyah, we don't have a שיעור
shiur for and we're very careful to never have שהייה, shehiyah, but
practically you could have and שהייה shehiyah applies not just to pausing
taking a nap and coming back. It applies to if you cut
out of the zone of שחיטה shechitah, while still cutting שחיטה shechitah
in the zone. Meaning הגרמה hagramah is if I'm going here and
I go up here and the animal dies by the wound up
here that's הגרמה, hagramah, which again you have to be careful but
you have to cut in the middle.
But if I for instance am holding the animal and I cut
my finger at the same time I'm doing שחיטה, Shechitah that's שהייה
shehiyah because the blade is now paused on my finger and come
back.
So that we're very careful for.
דריסה Drisah is obviously huge too.
I don't know if you've done דריסה, drisah, if you've applied pressure.
So it's a good question that I've pondered for a while. He's
given us examples but
you can דריסה drisah again, putting your finger on the back we
hold is דריסה. drisah. If you cut through the מפרקת, mifreket, the
spinal column, it's דריסה drisah because you can't get there otherwise unless
you're sawing forever then it's okay to cut through.
Are there animals when you bring the שחיטה that feel they go
to be killed?
Because
I heard them making a lot of noise.
So that's the work that Temple Grandin has done about keeping them
in. Generally chickens will make a lot of noise when they just
want to move and they can't move. So if you put them
in a small cage they make a lot of noise. If you've
ever driven past a cage of birds...
yeah, yeah, so and
how do you determine עיקור? ikor? עיקור Ikor is you assume that's
the beginning of a nick.
Well, עיקור ikor happens in two ways. עיקור Ikor can happen from
the actual cutting, it tears, meaning there's a פגימה pegimah and you
tore.
There's a conversation I think actually in one of the משניות mishnayot
that you guys have already passed about a what they call it,
an
אגל, agal, מגל magal right, the scythe or whatever they call it
which has serrations.
So they're talking about עיקור ikor when they talk about it might
be kosher if you do it in the opposite way of the
serrations because then you're not cutting. It's actually not, we don't hold
that it's kosher even בדיעבד Bedi'eved doing it that way.
But that's what they're talking about is if you go the one
way obviously there's עיקור ikor because it's tearing. So that's what a
פגימה pegimah is essentially. It's a little notch in the knife that
has edges. If this is the edge of the knife and there's
a פגימה, pegimah, then the edges will tear. The other option is
if these the סימנים are torn from the top or bottom of
what they're supposed to be connected to. That's why you press on
the שיפוי הכובע shipui hakova and it pops out because if it's
detached from the שיפוי הכובע shipui hakova it won't pop out.
How long will a knife last before it's retired?
How long will what last?
שחיטה knife last before it needs to be retired? Forever essentially?
I don't know I just started.
No, it does wear
out. However I've sort of looked down at it recently and I
have noticed that it's starting to bow a little bit, so I'll
have to eventually take off the ends a little bit.
I'm wondering, is this prong, is this prong used to drain the
blood afterwards? Is that where they put it in that...?
Yeah, we put it in essentially there's a traffic cone suspended over
a large trash barrel which has dirt prepared on the bottom. כיסוי
דם, Kisuy Hadam, yeah. Yeah, for כיסוי דם. Kisuy Hadam. And then
the bird goes into the cone so that it facilitates bleeding since
it's upside down.
And חלאדה Chalada would never really happen under normal circumstances, right? You'd
have to somehow get started in the middle.
Well, חלאדה Chalada can happen if you're using the wrong knife. Again,
a lot of these things we were proactive about. You can technically
שחט Shecht with a stick of bamboo if you get it sharp
enough, but we don't do that and we don't do that. I
mean you have to learn these things because if you're ever trapped
on an island and you're the only שוחט Shochet present. But
the guy who was teaching us actually said that, he's like you'll
need to know this because in case you're the only שוחט Shochet
on an island.
But the reason that the knife is flat on this edge is
precisely so חלאדה Chalada doesn't happen.
So you don't go into the middle of the neck.
Right, because if you could imagine that you started, pulled back, and
then you just sort of bumped your elbow or something and went
underneath the other סימן, Siman, that's חלאדה. Chalada. So by this being
like this you'll never really have that happen.
So you can't go through the neck from the front.
חלאדה Chalada can also happen if you do an animal the incorrect
way, meaning like if you ever see one of the many דקות
Dakot that are slaughtered, you ever see a בהמה דקה Behema Daka
slaughtered, you'll notice that they never do it while the animal is
just standing because the neck isn't long enough to turn and you
can't do it this way or it's חלאדה. Chalada. Because if you
do it this way, the animal's head is here I can't see
what I'm doing, which is the same as going underneath.
But technically it's כשר, Kosher, I mean the גמרא says it is,
but practically you don't do it.
Yeah, I mean I think he even says it's just not כשר.
Kosher. All right, I got it.
What's חלאדה, Chalada, what is חלאדה? Chalada?
חלאדה Chalada is when you're burrowing, yeah digging.
So you start in the middle and work out or you start
at the back and work forward.
So by דקה Daka generally they suspend them and then you take
the head and basically cradle it upwards so the animal's looking at
you, that way you can see what you're doing. Have you ever
tried traveling on a plane with...
I would never take this. No, I mean you know would you
show it to them and they put it somewhere? It's a practical
question.
I think yeah you'd have to check it.
I assume you'd have to.
You'd have to check it, so you'd have to have a better
case than I have because my case it would rattle.
But these are expensive not because of what you paid for it
raw but because of the hours and hours you've put in on
sharpening it, right?
That would be a great cop if I didn't buy it for
very expensive.
Really, it costs a lot even though you can go with an
unsharpened...?
Yeah, generally they're around two hundred dollars just for raw metal like
that.
Wow, really? Why is that? Just to get the metal that thin
to start with?
Because they can and there's not a whole lot of competition. They're
much more expensive in Israel. Much more expensive. They can be three
to five hundred dollars in Israel. The only one I've ever found
online which you can find at הסופר Hasofer which is an American
Judaic store in Israel in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they sell this size knife
for two hundred and seventy seven dollars. But it costs about fifty
dollars to ship to America so there you go.
So how much area do you have really in the chicken?
So it's an interesting question. I actually thought somebody was going to
ask me about giraffe.
Giraffe is כשר Kosher anyway or you gotta be totally like...?
It's actually not so clear. There's I've actually learned a lot from
the שוחט Shochet we're learning from now about giraffe and why you
can't maybe can't שחט Shecht giraffe. But there's a small amount of
range. It would be hard to end up in the wrong place.
Generally speaking with chickens it's pretty easy because when you pull them
over, I mean there's like a red line, it's hard to miss.
It's hard to miss.
With like roosters and things like that it's a little more difficult.
This thing about giraffe, there was an article about this a couple
years ago that from... what is it, Zivotofsky I think? He said
like a giraffe is like so easy because you could do it
anywhere on the neck and if you can't שחט Shecht a giraffe
you can't שחט Shecht anything.
Right, so there's a difference between לכתחילה Lechatchila and בדיעבד. בדיעבד you
can שחט Shecht anywhere on a giraffe as long as you don't
go into below the collarbone or up into the שיפוי הכובע. Shipuy
Hakova.
You get twelve feet.
Yeah, so you got like twelve feet but that's part of the
problem because לכתחילה Lechatchila you have to be exactly in the middle.
So get your tape measure and let's start counting.
However, I must appreciate לכתחילה because it's nowhere in the גמרא.
Yeah
so I mean he mentions it but the big problem is that
the מנהג Minhag for how to measure the middle... now here's where
the modern debate comes in where people get confused about why giraffe
is that...
If
you don't have a tradition for where to שחט shecht an animal
in the middle, the שמלה חדשה Simlah Chadashah does not say you
get out your tape measure and you measure. However, you could do
that in theory, which is one side of the debate. I can
measure it, therefore we're all good. The other theory or the the
halachic or minhagic tradition brought down is that you bend
the ear of the animal down and it will point to the
very middle of its neck. So if you don't have a tradition
of where exactly to cut it, you bend the animal's ear down,
which works very nice for cows and like three other animals.
Fortunately, most animals we have a tradition for. The problem is with
a giraffe, which we don't have a tradition of where to cut
it, which comes into the the excuse people give of we don't
have a מנהג minhag for it. So you could beat that if
you could bend its ear down, but its ears are about this
big and its neck is about this big. It doesn't even clear
its jawbone.
Aren't they endangered anyway?
They're endangered, so it's
a moot question.
No, but you could technically I think breed them in captivity. But
the the price per
the amount of anyway, because we do שחט shecht deer. I have
seen deer in כשר kosher restaurants.
Sure. There's a place in just up north west of West Point
that does deer that you can special order that's כשר. kosher.
And that's
the the deer species in America is a new world species, so
we didn't... well actually the same thing with turkey, but that's a...
probably bend its ear down.
Okay great. Thank you so much.
My
pleasure.
Alright, קדיש דרבנן.
Kaddish DeRabbanan. We don't have
a מנין minyan
here. קדיש Kaddish for the chicken.
No, we have a
מנין.
minyan.
You want to דאוון? daven?
We'll all become vegetarians.
Can I just try to
say a קדיש דרבנן?
Kaddish
DeRabbanan?
Say קדיש, Kaddish, say קדיש. Kaddish. Nice. You want to דאוון? daven?
יתגדל ויתקדש שמה רבא בעלמא די ברא כרעותה
וימליך מלכותה בחייכון וביומיכון ובחיי.
Yisgadal v'yiskadash shme raba b'alma di vra chirutei v'yamlich malchutei b'chayeichon
uv'yomeichon uv'chayei.